Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim,
and I bet you're wondering what the holes
in these jeans are, and let's find out.
I'm going to go to the text now.
We finished the terrible
and wonderful story
of the Lady of the Blue Lotus, Utpala,
who became an arhat
and who made 500 arhats out of her nuns.
Here we continue with Pabongka Rinpoche's
Lam Rim lecture.
'DAS ZIN PAS NA MA MIN PAR MI 'GYUR TE
Just because your mom was in the past,
doesn't mean she's not your mom.
Just because the days of being
your mom were in the past,
doesn't mean she's not your mom.
DE 'GYUR NA TSE STOD
KYI MA YANG TSE SMAD KYI
MA MIN PAR 'GYUR
Then logically, if the
fact that she's passed,
if the fact that the time she's
been your mother is passed,
means she's not your mother,
then everybody's mother
is not their mother,
because everybody's mother
was their mother before,
in this life.
So that means, if your mom
is not your mother this year,
she was your mother last year,
then she's not your mother, right?
According to your logic,
if she's been your mother in the past,
she's not your mother now.
Okay, well, then the mom who
gave you birth in this life
is not your mom.
Because she gave you birth before.
This is Pabongka's argument.
KHA SANG GI MA YANG DE
RING GI MA MIN PAR 'GYUR TE
Even your mom from yesterday
wouldn't be your mom today,
because that's passed.
So if you went to visit
your mother yesterday,
then you came home today, then suddenly,
because the day changed,
she's not your mother anymore, right?
Because someone in the past
has been your mother, is
not your mother, according
to your logic. Why?
DE 'DAS ZIN PAS SO
Because it's passed, she's passed.
Yesterday is also passed.
'DI NI PHRA BA'I MI RTAG PA STE
This is interesting, he says,
"That's a kind of subtle impermanence."
PHRA BA means subtle,
MI RTAG PA means impermanent.
THOS PA MA BYAS PAS RTOGS PAR DKA' MOD
If you haven't had a Buddhist education,
with the Lam Rim or with the ACI courses,
then RTOGS PAR DKA'
it's difficult to grasp.
Subtle impermanence is difficult to grasp
if you are not trained formally.
If you haven't had
formal Buddhist training,
training in the classics,
Mixed Nuts Classics,
then it's going to be difficult,
RTOGS DKA' difficult to catch it.
MOD means look, I know
but let's try to take
it to a common example
and I think it will be
easier for you guys.
DPER NA let's take an example.
GZAN 'DI LTA BU
So of course Pabongka Rinpoche
is giving his Lam Rim lecture,
with a GZAN.
GZAN means the shawl
that the monks wear over their shoulders.
So he would have been giving his lecture
with his shawl over his shoulders.
'DI LTA BU YANG NA NING
So NA NING means last year,
it's an idiom.
NA NING means last year.
GSAR PA'I SKABS NA NING
Last year, this shawl I have
on my shoulders was new.
GSAR PA'I SKABS DRI MA CAN MIN
It wasn't stinky.
And you know, to be honest,
people use their shawl
for everything in the monastery.
So it does get kind of,
and I have known monks,
I lived with a monk
who said it was unhealthy to
take a shower in the winter.
So he wouldn't take a shower all winter.
He wouldn't wash his body all winter,
and so it does get kind of DRI MA CAN,
means 'mala', right?
It has a good smell.
BUG RDOL means get holes in it,
like holes in your jeans.
We have BUG RDOL,
the best example of BUG RDOL
in our culture, modern culture, is jeans,
the holes in your jeans.
So look, these jeans didn't
have these holes a year ago,
but this year they have holes.
So he says, "Look at
this shawl I have on."
Geshe Michael could say, "Look
at these jeans I have on."
You know, BUG RDOL,
they have holes in them.
But they didn't have
holes in them last year.
Did they? And they
weren't smelly last year.
But now they're smelly.
BUG RDOL YANG MED PA LA
DE'I RGYUN DENG SANG
GI GZAN 'DI DRI MA CAN
But you can't say these are not the jeans
that I bought last year.
It's a very profound proof.
It's a very profound way of teaching
us subtle impermanence.
- Look, do you have jeans on? - Yes.
- Do they have holes in them? - Yes.
- Did they have holes
in them last year? - No.
- Are they the same jeans?
- Well yeah, they're the
same jeans, they're my jeans.
So he says, "There you go,
now you understand subtle
impermanence, got it?"
But you cannot say that the jeans today
that have holes in them are not the jeans
that you bought at...what's that store?
Buckle, last year.
They are the jeans you bought last year.
They are the same jeans.
Why are we talking about that here?
Yeah, your mom's changed, she's different.
Maybe she's BUG RDOL,
maybe she's got a hole somewhere,
but it's still the same mom.
You can't say it's not the same mom.
Just because she looks
older or she's not around,
or something, you can't say
it's not the same mom. Come on.
It's the same jeans, right? It's logic.
BUG RDOL YANG MED PA LA
DE'I RGYUN DENG SANG
GI GZAN 'DI DRI MA CAN.
We're talking about the
flow of an object over time,
it's called RGYUN.
And the flow of your mom over time.
DRI MA CAN, BUG RAL CAN DU 'DUG PAS,
DE GNYIS THA DAD PA LTA BU YIN,
Are they separate,
or are they not separate, or are they one?
Are they two points on a stream,
or are they two unconnected things?
Is there a pair of jeans
last year that was new
from the store, and then
there is a pair of jeans
this year that has holes in it?
- Are they separate? - Yes.
- Are they connected by a stream? - Yes.
- Are they still the same jeans? - Yes.
- Is it still your mom? - Yes.
DE LTA NA'ANG SKYE BA SNGA
PHYI'I MA GNYIS KYIS AA MA
BYAS PA LA KHYAD MED DU BSAM
You got to follow
this train of thought until you realize
that there's no difference
between your mom in this life,
which is the jeans with the holes in them,
and the mom in your last life,
which is the new jeans, okay?
Your mom in your last
life is the new jeans,
and your mom in this life is the jeans,
the mom with the holes in it.
And they are one stream. It's one thing.
If they were your mom in this life,
and they were your mom in a previous life,
it's the same person.
It's the same person.
It's the same jeans.
KHYAD MED DU BSAM DGOS TE
You got to think about it.
NA NING SROG BSKYABS NA
DE'I DRIN DA LO YANG DRAN
DGOS PA BZHIN NO
I love this sentence.
I don't know why,
but this sentence has always stuck with me
over many years.
NA NING SROG BSKYABS
If someone saves your life,
in 2020. Maybe in 2021 you
can show some gratitude.
Okay? 2020 someone pulls you off
from an automobile accident or something,
saves your life. What? In
2021, you're going to say,
oh, that was last year.
This is 2021, I don't have
to be grateful anymore.
"Come on", he says.
DE LTAR YANG YANG SBYANGS
PAS MAR SHES RGYUD LA
SKYES PA'I TSAD NI
This is very beautiful.
TSAD means how do you know
when you got it.
TSAD means measure, right?
Like TSAD MA. Like pramana.
How do you know when you've reached
MAR SHES?
Which is kind of 1.5 of
the, how many?, 5 point...
RGYU 'BRAS MAN NGAG BDUN
7 points of how to get bodhicitta.
It's really 1.5. What's 1.0?
1.0 is equanimity.
1.5 is, it's kind of like a 1.5,
to realize they've been your mother.
So how do you know? And I love that in the
Buddhist scripture when
they say, with an emotion,
how do you know when you got it.
When can you say,
I have MAR SHES?
At what point can you say,
When can you say RGYUD LA SKYES?
RGYUD LA SKYES means I have got
that realization in my mind.
I really do think of everyone as my mom.
How do you know?
SEMS CAN GROG SBUR GCIG MTHONG BA NA'ANG
Even if you just see a
single ant crawling across
the bathroom downstairs in the building,
which used to happen.
SEMS CAN GROG SBUR GCIG MTHONG
especially when
you are sitting and
meditating in the bathroom,
you see an ant crawling around.
MTHONG BA NA'ANG RANG DE'I BUR GYUR SKABS
There was a time
when I was this being's child.
When you see an ant crawling on the floor
of the bathroom and you're
sitting there meditating,
and you automatically think,
I was once this ant's child.
I was once the baby of this ant.
SKYID SDUG TSANG MA DE LA RE DOGS
Misspelled in the original
text, very subtle.
RE DOGS means all my hopes and fears
depended on this person.
Whether I was going to have
a good day or a bad day,
whether I was going to
survive today or not,
depended on this person.
So, if you're sitting in the bathroom
and you see an ant
crawling across the floor,
and you think, there was a
day when I was her child,
and my very life depended
on her from hour to hour.
BYUNG BA LHANG LHANG
means... what do you call it? un-evoked?
I don't know, LHANG LHANG means
when that comes up in your heart uncalled?
Yeah just totally spontaneously.
You're not thinking
I should feel compassion or
I should feel this emotion,
but just the emotion
takes over your heart.
LHANG LHANG, like that.
Oh wow, this is the one
that I was looking for
to survive the day, this bug.
MAR SHES RGYUD LA BYUNG BA
then you've got MAR SHES.
And he uses the honorific word for born,
'KHRUNGS PA is SKYE PA.
It's a very telling verb choice.
He says thou hast given
birth in your holy heart to
MAR SHES.
He's using the high honorific
that we would use to a Buddha.
It means if you could get to that point,
where you had this emotion about
a single ant crawling across the floor,
then you're really a high practitioner.
JO BO RJE LTA BU DGOS TSUL BCAS GSUNGS
You guys have to be like Atisha,
like Lord Atisha.
This is how he would feel about an ant.
When you can feel about an ant
the way that Atisha
would feel about an ant, automatically,
despite yourself,
then you have MAR SHES.
So I guess we'll never get there.
You got an ant picture for me?
This is, I found this picture,
this little girl playing with ants.
I guess you must have
done that. I did that.
We used to kill them
actually, which is really bad.
But she's playing with ants.
Maybe she's having those thoughts.
With this, we have reached 2.0.
We have reached the
second of the seven steps
for developing bodhicitta.
And that's called DRIN DRAN
Say DRIN DRAN
It's not Ting Ting, it's DRIN DRAN
DRIN DRAN means to recall the kindness.
BKA' DRIN DRAN PA
BKA' DRIN means kindness,
DRAN PA means to remember.
DRIN DRAN is the short word.
DRIN DRAN
Second step. Don't forget
what we're talking about.
We're talking about actually
six steps you can do
to reach a seventh result,
which is bodhicitta.
Supposedly, if you just go through
these steps one by one,
you'll get to bodhicitta
without thinking about
it, which is really cool.
That's the purpose of the Lam Rim.
The Lam Rim means just do this meditation,
then do that meditation,
and then, even if you don't
want to, you're going to be
a bodhisattva.
DE LTAR SEMS CAN RNAMS
AA MA YIN PAR MNYAM NA,
AA MA BYAS SKABS DRIN SHIN
TU CHE BAR BSAM DGOS PAS
So I think all of us,
because of the old jeans,
we are closer to believing
that everyone has been our mom before.
But how did she treat
us when she was our mom?
What did she do for us?
So let's talk about that.
Let's talk about DRIN SHIN TU CHE
SKABS DRIN SHIN TU CHE
When she was our mom,
how did she treat us?
Here we go.
DA LTA TSE 'DI'I MA 'DI LTA BUR MTSON NA
MTSON hear means, it can mean weapon, like
MTSON CHA'I 'KHOR LO
-- The Crown of Knives,
but MTSON can also mean
to take as an example.
So here, it's to take as an example.
Let's take as an example,
let's just talk about
the mom you had in this life.
THOG MTHA' BAR GSUM DU DRIN CHE STE
She has been kind to you.
THOG MTHA' BAR -- This is a famous idiom.
Do you guys know THOG MTHA' BAR?
Tsongkapa wrote a poem called
THOG MTHA' BAR
It means in the beginning,
in the end, and in-between.
In the beginning, in
the end, and in-between.
So she has been extremely
kind to us in the beginning,
in the end, and in all the time between.
THOG MAR ZLA DGU NGO BCU
What's the beginning?
It's in the womb. She carried you for
ZLA DGU
nine months.
Then he says NGO BCU,
which means ten days.
Tibetans believed that normal term is
nine months and ten days.
Is it true? I don't know.
(unclear)
TBAR LUS LA KHUR BA
There's KHUR BA again, Tim.
She bore that burden.
She carried that burden for
nine months and ten days.
BU LA GNOD KYIS DOGS NAS
This DOGS means suspicion.
And here it means
worried that something
might happen to her child.
Worried that something
RANG NYID KYIS ZAS SKOM
'GRO 'DUG THAMS CAD GZAB
GZAB GZAB in modern Tibetan,
GZAB GZAB means be super careful.
GZAB GZAB BYED
Like if someone is
I don't know, using a sharp
knife to cut something,
the mom might say GZAB GZAB
GZAB GZAB BYED
Be careful. Here it means
Just deciding ZAS
Just deciding SKOM
Just deciding 'GRO
Just deciding 'DUG
She would GZAB GZAB
She would try to proceed
with great caution about,
ZAS means what she eats,
SKOM means what she drinks,
'GRO means the manner
in which she walks, and
'DUG means the manner in which she sits.
So she would be cautious
about even what she drank
because she would be thinking,
how will it affect my child?
How will it affect my child?
If I walk quickly, will it hurt the child?
If I sit in a certain way,
will that hurt the child?
She's always thinking of the child.
Intense caring.
I got a picture here for you.
On a good day, I guess,
all of us who are pregnant
would decide to eat the salad,
just for the baby, even though salads are
an anathema,
are terrible.
She would eat a salad just for the baby.
She's not thinking about herself.
She's thinking about the baby.
DE'I TSE MAS DE LTAR
BSKYANGS MKHAS PA ZHIG
MA BYUNG PHYIN
This is a difficult sentence.
DE'I TSE means
if in those pregnant days,
MAS is instrumental.
If my mom
DE LTAR BSKYANGS means
to sustain a certain behavior
If she had not been a MKHAS PA
What's a MKHAS PA?
Like Kedrup Tenpa Dargye, Kedrup Je,
Yeah, like a master. If
she had not been a master
in deciding what to eat and drink
and how to walk and how to sit,
if she had not been a
master of considering
her child's welfare,
MA BYUNG PHYIN means in that eventuality,
In that case, MA BYUNG PHYIN
if she had not been so
mindful about what to eat,
what to do, then you and I wouldn't be
in the Lam Rim right now.
It's a very beautiful sentence.
You and I wouldn't be here
listening to the Lam Rim.
We would have died. We would be retarded,
or we wouldn't have made it here
if she had not taken those care
before we came out.
So it's a very compelling
argument to a big bunch of monks.
Here's a big bunch of monks
who enjoy their Geshe classes,
and then Pabongka says,
he doesn't say she saved
your life, bla bla bla.
He says, "You wouldn't have studied
Abhisamayalankara if it hadn't been
for your mom."
Oh my God, can you imagine?
You wouldn't have ever heard of
Middle Way.
And then all the monks
are like, "Oh, my God".
Our moms are so cool.
RANG RE DA LTA means
all of us sitting here right now
CHOS DANG MJAL
This MJAL is
a very important word
in Buddhist language.
It means to encounter a holy thing.
MJAL -- like when you,
I remember people would come to see
the Mongolian Temple where I lived.
And they would come to
see the paintings mostly.
I would tell my teacher, Rinpoche,
I'd say, I'm going to go
show them the paintings.
He'd say, "No, no, no. We don't
say show them the paintings.
They are going to meet the Holy Dharma."
You have to say CHOS DANG MJAL
Say CHOS DANG MJAL
(students repeating)
CHOS means dharma.
DANG means with.
MJAL means meet.
Meet with the dharma.
So you don't say, "I'm going
to go look at paintings."
You say, "I'm going to
go meet the Holy Dharma."
It's a beautiful word.
So you wouldn't have had the chance
to CHOS DANG MJAL if your mom
hadn't been careful
drinking what she drank
when you were in her womb.
DAM PA'I CHOS LA SLOB
TU YOD PA 'DI MI 'BYUNG
AYou wouldn't be here today
studying the Holy Dharma
if your mom had not taken great care,
even in the womb, even in the womb.
And for a person who really
values their dharma life,
then that's a very huge argument.
That's a huge piece of logic.
- You better be nice to your mom. - Why?
- Because she's why you're
sitting in the Lam Rim right now.
Can you imagine not being
in the Lam Rim right now?
I know what I would be.
I would be a professor at
Princeton or something.
And I would be unhappy, and
I would have two divorces,
and I'd be drinking wine every night
to make my life a little more bearable and
struggling against my colleagues to see
who could publish a book
first. And I would be there.
I know. So, I'm grateful.
T'DI DAG KYANG RANG NYID RGOD
DRAGS NAS BYUNG BA MIN GYI
This is very funny because RGOD
this is the RGOD in BYING RGOD
BYING BA and RGOD PA
Meditation obstacles.
Dullness and agitation.
So this RGOD means agitation.
What's the word for a chimpan-,
a large, what do you call it, chimpanzee?
What's the large, smaller than an ape,
bigger than a monkey?
I'm sorry, smaller than a
gorilla, bigger than a monkey?
Chimpanzee?
[Student] Orangutang?
[GMR] Yeah, orangutang.
What's the Tibetan word for orangutang?
MI RGOD
Agitated human.
So RGOD DRAGS
This DRAGS with this RGOD means
your effort and your cleverness.
The fact that you're sitting
here in a dharma class,
or in a Mixed Nuts class,
with the holiest of dharma,
was not because you were so clever
or you were so, you were so sharp
that you got yourself here.
It's just that your mom
drank the right thing
while she was pregnant.
And if she had drunk something else,
you wouldn't have had
the brains to sit here.
And that's true, right, so...
MIN GYI, AA MA DE NYID KYI DRIN
It's only your mom.
DE NYID means it's only,
all the credit goes to your
mom that you have a brain
to sit here in Lam Rim. Think about it.
She could have taken drugs.
She could have done other things.
She could have drunk alcohol.
You could be mentally
dull from her misbehavior
while you were, while she was pregnant,
but she took take of you even then.
She started... When you think
about the mother's kindness,
DRIN DRAN, step number 2,
don't start with after your birth.
Start from after your conception.
She started taking care of you then.
Probably even before conception, right?
So I like this photo.
When I think about... I
said, I'm going to go find
a picture of a Lam Rim teaching
that we'd been through,
so I can say that we were there.
And I love this picture.
This is a Lam Rim that we had in Bali,
recently like a year ago.
And this is the Vietnamese contingent.
These are the students from Vietnam.
They did a beautiful dance.
Then the Japanese did a nice dance.
And then the Chinese did a nice dance.
And for us to stand there and
watch this beautiful dance
in the middle of a highest teaching,
you wouldn't be there if
your mom had abused her body
while she was pregnant.
She was taking care of
you before you came out.
BAR DU SKYES PA NA'ANG
GANG YANG MI SHES PA
Now, he says,
BAR THOG MTHA' BAR
THOG means in the beginning.
MTHA' means at the end.
BAR means in-between.
Let's talk about BAR.
BAR starts when you come out.
The in-between starts after
your born from the womb.
BAR DU SKYES PA NA'ANG
Even after you were born,
you are a
GANG YANG MI SHES PA SHA'I 'BU
You are a lump of stupid flesh
that doesn't know anything.
You are a ball of meat
that don't know nothing.
That sounds like a good thing
you can call people that upset you.
You're just a ball of meat
who don't know nothing.
I love this sentence, I don't know why.
This sentence stays with me also.
You were just a ball of stupid meat.
SOR BCU'I means
SOR here means fingers and
SOR BCU'I RTZE LA BLANGS means to
I don't know,
to hold something up on
your fingers like that.
She's laying. She just had
her guts ripped out by you,
and she almost died,
and then she's got this
little, stupid ball of meat.
And she's like, "Oh, you're so beautiful."
And she's like, holds you
up on her ten fingers.
And I saw a picture of Nour
like this a month ago. She's like,
we were following the hospitals today.
It's the usual drama:
She went to the hospital. Her water broke.
She went to hospital.
They race to the hospital.
Okay, is it out yet? No, no, no.
Then, you know, you do
your work. Have dinner.
You call Seiji. -Is it out yet? - No.
- She's screaming. -Okay I got it.
And then you keep,
sometimes you forget to call Seiji.
Next morning you're
like, "I forgot to call
Seiji last night."
You call, say, "Is it out yet?"
- No, she's still screaming.
And then suddenly your phone rings,
and you got this photo
of Nour with the baby
like this. Ain't it the truth?
It's always been like that.
BAR DU
SKYES PA NA'ANG
She is SOR BCU'I RTZE LA BLANGS
She's holding you on the tips
of her ten fingers. Then,
RNYED PA LTA BU'I DGA' TSOR BYAS
She looks blissed out
like she's just found
a bag of diamonds.
It's so funny. It's such
a funny picture to me.
She's not saying,
"You almost killed me two hours ago."
She's like, "Oh, look at this
beautiful, precious thing."
Like she found a new bag
of diamonds or something.
She's treating this ball of
stupid meat, ball of idiot meat,
that would make a good name for a band,
She's treating you like a
bag of diamonds or something.
Oh look, I found a bag of diamonds.
You can see these pictures.
This is a universal picture.
It's not hard to find this picture.
BU DE SOR BCU'I RTZE LA BLANGS
GTER RNYED PA LTA BU'I DGA' TSOR BYAS
DGA' TSOR means she's blissed out.
SHA'I DROD LA BCAR
SHA'I DROD means the warmth of her body.
This is one of the levels of SBYOR LAM.
Was it? DROD RTZE MO CHOS MCHOG
DROD, RTZE MO, BZOD PA, CHOS MCHOG
So DROD means warmth.
In philosophical terms also,
getting close to an
emptiness is called warmth.
Here, SHA'I DROD means her flesh.
The warmth of her flesh.
BCAR means she presses you
to the warmth of her flesh.
'JAM PA'I STAN LA BZHAG
She tries to find
places to put you which are 'JAM PA,
like 'JAM PA'I DBYANGS
What's the Sanskrit?
Manju.
And that's a common
name for women in India,
Manju.
Gentle or velvety, or something like that.
So when she lays you down,
she tries to find a
nice, soft place for you.
A manju place for you.
That's a good way to remember Manjushri.
And then, BRTZE BA'I 'DZUM GYIS BSUS,
this is the BSUS that
the Buddha did to Utpala
when he first saw her,
greeted, he greeted you.
This BSUS means to greet.
And she greets with you a BRTZE BA'I 'DZUM
means a smile of total love.
You just ripped my guts out.
I was bleeding all over the place.
They just sewed me up.
The painkillers are wearing off.
I love you. You're so beautiful.
It's crazy, right?
SNABS LAS PAS PHYI CHOG PA
SNABS means snot
that comes out of a kid's
nose. It is, I'm sorry.
LAG PAS PHYI CHOG PA
CHOG PA means to allow
or to be appropriate.
Like when you ask your
teacher, can I leave now?
You say 'GRO CHOG PA -- can I leave now?
Can I, do you need me for anything else?
This CHOG PA means she could have,
it would have been okay if
she wiped your snot with her
LAG PA, from your nose,
with her hand, with her fingers. But,
GNOD DOGS, this is the DOGS we just had.
She's afraid it might
hurt you. So she wipes it
with her KHA,
[Student] Mouth.
Yeah, she wipes the snot out
of your nose with her lips,
because she's afraid her
fingers might be too rough.
DOGS
MI GTZANG BA
Your poo poo,
SHING LA SOGS PAS BRAD
She could
scrape it out with some
plastic spoon or something,
but she uses her LAG PA,
her hands, because she's
afraid it might irritate
your bottom, like a spoon
or some kind of cloth
or something, and she
uses her own fingers.
PHYIS means to wipe.
ZHABS PHYIS means, what's that mean?
Shoe shiner -- ZHABS PHYIS.
It's the Tibetan word
for a Lama's attendant.
The polite Tibetan word
for Lama's attendant
is ZHABS PHYIS.
Wiper of the holy shoes.
Hey Holy Shoe Wiper,
what's Rinpoche want for dinner today?
Or something like that.
Okay Jigme?
DE'I SKABS SU RANG NYI MA
GCIG GAM CHU TSOD GCIG TZAM
RING YAL BAR DOR NA'ANG
Now if she had decided to take a break
and leave us alone for
a day, or even an hour.
NYI MA GCIG means a day,
GAM means or,
CHU TSOD GCIG means one hour,
if she had decided, you
know let me take a break,
I'm going to go,
go see a movie or something,
in a theater.
YAL BAR DOR means to leave you,
YAL DOR means to abandon somebody.
If she had left me for a day,
24 hours, or even one hour,
and gone to see a movie,
or gone to have fun with her friends,
YANG NA KHYIS ZA BA'AM
maybe a dog would come and eat me,
which happens. Or
YANG NA BYAS 'THOG
YANG NA
or else maybe I could be
carried away by a large bird.
And I've seen small animals
carried away by birds
in the desert. Baby animals
do get carried away by birds.
It could happen to a human.
There's a story of the first Dalai Lama.
His parents' camp was attacked by bandits.
His mom hid him in some rocks,
and came back to fight.
Then when they went to find him,
he was being protected by
a large vulture or eagle.
It was standing over him.
Anyway, it could happen that
I was carried away by a bird.
G-YANG DU LHUNG BA
Or I could fall off a table
or off a chair and break my head open.
This G-YANG means fall into
a canyon or some kind of cliff,
fall of a cliff. Babies do that.
SOGS KYIS 'CHI BAR 'GYUR BA LAS 'OS MED
I would have died if she had abandoned me
for even an hour or a day.
I would have died.
Possible, I would have died.
NYI MA RE RER YANG SROG
MGO BRGYA BRGYA BTON
She saved our life hundreds
of times every day.
And you can see it. I'm working
with Seiji everyday on Zoom.
He has a new baby, his wife Nour,
by the way, they got married yesterday.
They got their paperwork.
She never, never, moms have this instinct
not to be distracted for even
a moment from their child.
She's totally linked in to the child.
She's aware if there is anything
dangerous around the child.
Slightly dangerous.
And she's totally aware of
how's the child's security
at any moment.
If she hadn't been like that,
we surely would have died.
BU LA SDUG BSNGAL
I have a close friend, close friend of
my teacher who's child
was crushed by a truck
because she looked away for
a moment. And it happens.
They can't run. They can't
think. They just sit there.
BU LA SDUG BSNGAL BYUNG BA LAS RANG LA
SDUG BSNGAL BYUNG BA ZHE NAS
If she had to make a choice
between my child suffers
or I suffer, she would
always choose I suffer.
This 'DAM means to choose.
ZHING THA NA GNYID KYI TSE 'ANG
THA NA means in the end,
in the extreme.
GNYID KYI TSE 'ANG
Even when she's asleep,
part of her mind is still
looking at her child,
still watching her
child, even in her sleep.
SNGAR RGYUN LTAR GYI
LHOD BDEK NYAL MA PHOD
She never sleeps
as solidly as she used to,
before she had the baby.
She never sleeps as soundly as she did
Her sleep is always half
sleep, because she's thinking
is something happening to the baby.
All right, and here we have a mother
checking her child in the sleep.
I think nowadays, even when we are,
I'm going through this as a grandpa.
I have a new grandkid, Maitri,
and I can see that they've learned.
Seiji and Nour have learned not to sleep.
They've learned to sleep
halfway all the time.
And it's interesting, and it's beautiful.
So just think about the fact that your mom
did this for you, and
that the ant crawling
across the bathroom
floor did this for you.
We'll continue with DRIN
DRAN in the next episode.